This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
Today,
we're going to have our first encounter
with what is called gauge theory.
All of modern physics is based all of
modern particle physics in particular
and modern general relativity,
gravity physics,
all fundamental views of physics and a
great deal I might add in condensed
matter physics, not that I don't think
that condensed matter physics is
fundamental. I should not have made that
distinction,
but condensed matter physics
um particle physics
general relativity
the one of the most basic principles is
the principle of gauge invariance. I'm
sure you've all heard of it.
You probably wonder what it is. Some of
you may know what it is.
Uh we're going to
begin
with our study of gauge symmetry or
gauge invariance
gauge principle
by studying a simple example.
Now
in 1905
Einstein pointed to the importance
uh of
very carefully
defining carefully and setting up the
idea of coordinate systems
that
there may be
some hidden assumptions that one makes
when one speaks of things like well,
simultaneity is of course one of them,
but other such things, the length of
objects and so forth and that you really
do have to be very careful to
operationally and carefully define what
you mean
by
various kinds of concepts such as
simultaneity for example. Uh
So everybody thinks that they know what
simultaneity means,
but comparing times at different places
is not so obvious how you compare, how
you say when two times are equal when
they correspond to different places,
especially since it takes light time to
go from one place to another. So he was
very careful
and in being careful, he invented the
special theory of relativity.
But that um how should I say that
idea
of being careful about defining
relative things at different places of
space and the ambiguities that could
inherently be there
because you're trying to compare things
at different locations
uh that um
theme has sort of permeated physics
since Einstein's time.
The general theory of relativity makes
it even worse that not only can't you
compare detailed simultaneity,
but you can't even compare for example
in an obvious way what you might mean by
my finger is pointing that way over
here. You point your finger in some
direction. You point your finger in some
direction. Good. Are we pointing our
fingers in the same direction or not?
How do we tell? Well, we're looking and
in looking we transfer photons back and
forth and so forth. And so we make
comparisons by sending photons back and
forth. But how do we decide without you
know, without an experiment to send
something back and forth, how do we
decide whether this and this are really
pointing in the same direction or not?
Right? Well, one way is to try to
carefully bring this over to here and
see if they're pointing in the same
direction when we line them up. But how
do I know that in the process of going
from here to here I didn't rotate my
finger?
And
of course in the back of our imagination
we imagine that there is located at each
point of space an idealized
coordinate reference frame that are
oriented parallel to each other when we
move from one place to another, but
maybe that's a maybe that's a
idea that um
is
a little too naive. Maybe we have to be
more careful in comparing things.
Now, we compare all kinds of things,
but the specific thing I want to talk
about is comparing the phase of complex
wave fields.
A very very important example
of comparisons at different points
has to do with complex wave fields. Now,
remember a complex wave complex fields,
we've discussed them. I called a field
phi
when it happened to be made out of two
real components
phi 1 plus i phi 2.
And of course, I can either think of
them as complex
fields and their and their complex
conjugate
or I can just think of
Incidentally, this phi and this phi are
the same thing. I sometimes
draw it this way and sometimes draw it
this way.
Uh that's one way of thinking of a
complex field as a complex field. The
other way of thinking about it is a pair
a pair of real fields. In which case, we
would say at every point in space
we have a set of axes, one of which we
call phi 1 and one of which we call phi
2 and at every point in space, the field
takes on some value.
At this point over here, the field might
be oriented our complex scalar field
might be located at this point. At that
point over here, might be located at
this point.
But in saying something like that, we're
implicitly assuming that there's some
kind of way of relating
directions in the space at different
points of space.
Uh let's just to get this idea and to
pin this idea down, let's go back to the
jump rope analogy. The jump rope analogy
for the complex field is just that we
have a string, a long string, could be a
rope.
And that rope is at every point free to
move
in two directions,
up and down and right and left from my
perspective over here. I should have
brought in a rope. I always ah
Want to play jump rope?
Yeah, okay, good.
I don't know what
This is not going to go very far. All
we're going to do is swing the rope
around, but okay, let's do it anyway.
Yeah, all right, you take what you take
that and good. Okay. So this is a rope
which when we stretch out is like this,
but it's actually free to move both
horizontally and vertically. And then it
has the capacity not just to vibrate,
but to vibrate in a way that
that has some angular momentum. Now, in
order to
explain what not to explain, but in
order to describe the configuration of
this string, I have to tell you not just
how far
from the origin, the origin now means
the straight string when it's as
straight as possible,
how not only how far it's been
displaced, but at what angle it's been
displaced.
Right? So I have to describe both either
a complex number at every point, complex
number could be x plus iy for the
position of the string,
or thank you.
Or I could describe it either a pair of
coordinates, a complex number, or an
angle and a radius, any number of ways
of describing it.
But it's implicit in
implicit in describing things that the
coordinate axes x and y that I use over
here on the string are parallel to the
coordinate axes over here, are parallel
to the coordinate axes over here.
So we have made an assumption that it is
possible to compare angles at different
points and say whether they're the same
or not the same.
Uh it is not completely obvious that
that's a good assumption.
In fact, really honestly, when one takes
general relativity into account in the
motion of strings and so forth, it is
not so obvious and in fact, it's not
even true that there's a unique way of
comparing angles at different places.
But we're not talking about angles in
real space now. We're talking about
angles in a fictitious field space,
which is mathematically similar to the
rotation of the jump rope,
but we're talking about angles
in a
mathematical field space.
And this situation comes up when we ask
questions like is the value of the
complex field at one location the same
as it is at another location or not?
In order to answer that question, we
have to compare angles in this among
other things, angles in the space at
different points.
Now, here's what we know. For some field
theories, for some field theories,
namely those which have a concept of
charge,
that there is an invariance, a symmetry.
And the symmetry corresponds to rotating
the coordinates phi 1 and phi 2.
Rotating them to the some new direction
or equivalently, what's equivalently is
rotating
the uh position of the field
in not in space, but in phi1 phi2 space.
So, we either rotate the axes or
actually physically change the value of
the field by rotating it. In either
case, the coordinates of the field will
change.
So,
we could imagine a symmetry
transformation of the fields
which
can either, as I said, be described by
physically changing the configuration or
just changing the coordinates that we
use to describe the field.
And we know how to describe that. We can
describe it trigonometrically,
that phi2 prime is equal to cosine of an
angle and so forth.
Uh
but we can also describe it in complex
notation very, very neatly.
The transformation
that corresponds to rotation of
coordinates
can just be written
phi prime
that's the value of the field after, or
the value of the coordinates of the
field, after you've rotated the
coordinates
is equal
to e to the i theta
times phi, the unrotated
notation for the field. Where theta is
just the angle of rotation here. Now, I
hope nobody gets confused between thetas
and phis. Phis are fields.
Theta is just an angle of rotation in
this field space
uh of the coordinates which describe
the field.
Now, this is an operation that we can do
on a field. It corresponds in the case
of uh of the jump rope to going at every
point in the jump rope and changing the
angle by the same amount. By the same
amount, that's the key phrase.
By the same amount, theta
is just a number and it rotates the
field in the field space
sort of rigidly.
Rigidly everywhere by the same amount.
That's a symmetry, for example, of the
Lagrangian that we studied last time.
Which what was it? It was d mu
phi star
d mu phi
Question? Yeah, is phi prime relative to
Is that the Phi prime It's not
Relative to the green line,
Yeah, yeah, that's right. Phi Phi could
be the coordinates relative to the black
line. Uh phi prime could be the
coordinates relative to the blue line,
green line.
Hm? Isn't it e to the minus i theta?
Cuz the angle's getting smaller
when you rotate by positive theta. Yeah,
uh it doesn't
You may be right, but uh
uh if it's invariant, then the
multiplication by a phase like this for
every angle, it includes negative angles
and positive angles, so
uh
uh quite possibly for this particular
setup over here, I may have
inadvertently put the wrong sign here,
but it it doesn't matter for anything.
Uh good. So, let's uh
let's change the orientation to conform
correctly to the formula.
Probably You're probably right
that
that I've rotated the coordinates the
other way.
All right. So, phi prime And besides
which, I haven't told you which was phi
and which was phi prime.
So, there's no way uh to compare it on
I guess I guess we would call Let's see,
we'll call the coordinates
here phi prime.
Now, I think we fixed it.
And phi phi1 prime and phi2 prime.
Okay. Uh
this is either right or wrong, and I
don't really care.
Um
good. Now, we studied some Lagrangians.
We studied the Lagrangian, the
derivative of phi star times the
derivative of phi. These are complex
conjugates of each other.
We added it for fun another term. I
think it was minus mu squared phi star
phi.
And this Lagrangian is invariant under
this operation. The reason is because if
phi is replaced by phi prime
and phi star prime, or phi prime star,
is e to the minus i theta
phi.
And furthermore, the same is true of the
derivatives.
Supposing I differentiate phi prime, the
derivative of phi prime with respect to
x, let's pick a particular coordinate,
with respect to x, is equal to what?
Theta here is just a constant for my
purposes right now. And so, when I
differentiate phi prime, I get nothing
from differentiating the e to the i
theta, that just stays there
times derivative of phi with respect to
x.
So, the derivatives that appear here
also themselves just get rotated by the
same phase angle.
When you multiply them by their complex
conjugates
the e to the i thetas cancel.
E to the i thetas cancel here.
And so, this is an example of a
Lagrangian which is invariant
invariant
with
respect to
phi goes to phi
e to the i theta.
Okay. Now, you might ask, um what would
happen though? Is it invariant
with respect to rotations of this plane
which vary from place to place as you
move along?
For example,
we could ask exactly this about the
rope. It really does have to do very
deeply with the question of whether you
can compare these angles at different
places.
Uh
to say that the Lagrangian is invariant
under phase
means that you don't have an invariant
sense of what
angle zero means. You can rotate the
whole picture.
But
comparing angle zero at different places
is meaningful.
But supposing that you have Supposing
this Lagrangian turns out to be
invariant under a stronger symmetry.
A symmetry where you rotate
the angle
at each point by a arbitrary angle which
might differ from point to point.
In other words,
let's investigate whether the Lagrangian
we've written down is invariant under
uh
under a symmetry
where we allow theta to be a function of
x.
That means as we move along from point
to point in space
we rotate the axes differently.
If there is no good sense in which you
can compare
angles at different places then we would
expect this to be just as good a
symmetry
as when we when we rigidly rotate.
So, we can think about this as the
difference between a kind of rigid
rotation and a rotation which varies
from place to place.
Okay. Also x here.
Well, let's examine that question. First
of all, let's look Let Let me
Let me remember that we're supposed to
integrate this over space, and the full
action would be integral d4x.
Uh
let's look at the various terms in this
Lagrangian and see whether they change
or not when we do such an operation.
Well, what happens to phi star phi?
That's an easy one.
Phi star phi, phi gets multiplied by e
to the i theta, phi star gets multiplied
by e to the minus i theta at each point
separately those phase angles cancel.
So, this term in the Lagrangian
is fully invariant
under these position-dependent
Let's call them position-dependent phase
rotations.
There's another name for
position-dependent phase transformation.
It is
gauge transformation. That is what a
gauge transformation is.
Or at least this is a special case
of the more general concept.
More general concept
any kind of symmetry you can imagine
doing it differently from point to
point.
All right. So, this term, we could check
it off. This term here is invariant. Red
check means that that term means that
that term is invariant.
What about these terms
which involve derivatives of phi?
If this is going to show up anywheres,
it's going to show up in questions
having to do with how phi varies from
place to place, and whether when we
compare phi at one point with another
with a neighboring point
whether this Lagrangian is invariant.
So, let's check.
Let's Here Let's calculate.
All right. Let's
Let's see. I think uh do I want to
switch the definition of phi and phi
prime? I may.
Uh just to conform with my notes. No, I
think I have it the way I want it.
Okay. So,
this is the primed field. Here's the
unprimed field.
Let's calculate
And here's the
uh and
yeah, you know what? Let's um
Right.
Let's write the Lagrangian in terms of
the prime variables.
Prime, unprimed, what's the difference?
We can just change just changing names.
Let's just changing names of what we
call the field variable.
Here's the Lagrangian for the prime
field.
Let's work it out now since we know the
relationship between the prime and the
unprimed field, let's work out whether
this Lagrangian has exactly the same
form if we substitute for phi prime
phi.
All right, the first thing we have to do
is figure out what happens to the
derivative of phi of phi prime
with respect to x mu.
That appears in the Lagrangian, but I
want to rewrite it in terms of phi.
All right, but now I have when I
differentiate
when I differentiate, I get two terms. I
get one from differentiating this factor
and one from differentiating this
factor.
The first term, well, let's take the
first term to be the simpler one when
you differentiate phi. That just gives
you d phi by d x mu
times e to the i theta of x.
This doesn't worry me because I expect
that when this is multiplied by the
complex conjugate, it's going to go
away.
All right, but then let's take the other
term. The other term
you differentiate e to the i theta of x
and multiply by phi.
All right, so what's the derivative of e
to the i theta of x?
That is i
times the derivative of theta with
respect to x
times e to the i theta.
I've used the derivative of an
exponential
is just equal to the derivative of
what's in the exponential times the
exponential itself.
So
both the terms have an e to the i theta.
That's a good thing because that will
probably cancel when we multiply by the
complex conjugate.
But we now have this gradient or this
derivative of the phase angle.
Derivative of the transformation phase
angle.
And that's not so obvious that that will
cancel out. In fact, it won't.
So let's rewrite now the Lagrangian in
terms of phi instead of phi prime. It's
just a change of variables. It's just a
change of what we meant by the field.
And let's see what we get.
Now we get integral
d mu phi star.
Uh let's see.
I should write down what happens to the
derivative of phi star.
The derivative of phi star phi prime
star with respect to x mu, what happens
to it?
You just complex conjugate. That's equal
to the derivative of phi star with
respect to x
e to the minus i theta.
That's the complex conjugate of this
factor. And then the complex conjugate
here is minus i
d theta by d x mu
times e to the minus i theta of x
times phi star.
All right, the minus came because the
derivative because the complex conjugate
of i is minus i. All right, is everybody
happy with this?
If not, stop me now and I'll explain
what's on the blackboard.
You put a star in the second term. Uh
star on which second term? There here.
Here? Yeah. Where? You you just
Yeah, there's a star there. Oh. Yeah.
Hm?
Phi star here, yeah, good.
Phi star here, right.
Okay, now
if I didn't have to worry about this
term here
I would just multiply these two. If I
didn't have any x dependence in theta,
for example, if x was if theta was
independent of x these terms would not
be here and I would just be multiplying
this by this and the e to the i phis
would cancel and I would find out that
this Lagrangian was exactly equal
to the same thing except replacing phi
prime by phi.
Okay? But it's not true now. Let's work
work out what we have. We have d by d mu
of phi star
times let me factor out the e to the
minus i theta minus i
d theta by d x mu
times phi star.
Now I kept for last e to the minus i
theta. Let's put it there.
Now we have to multiply that by the
complex conjugate. The derivative of phi
or the derivative of phi prime. That
comes from here. Each term has an e to
the plus i theta
which will cancel with the e to the i
theta here. So that's good.
That e to the i theta cancels as before.
And what are we left with? We're left
with d phi by d x mu
plus i
d theta by d x mu
phi.
Let's add back in this minus
mu squared
phi star phi.
All right, so the cost of replacing phi
star phi prime by phi by this position
dependent rotated phi
is some extra terms in the Lagrangian.
And so the Lagrangian does not have the
same form that it started with.
It has a different form. It now has
things in it. Now theta is not the is
not really a degree of freedom. It's
just an arbitrary angle that we chose to
vary throughout space in an arbitrary
way. But when we see we do that the
structure the the the form of the
Lagrangian changes. It's not a symmetry.
It's only a symmetry if the Lagrangian
would have come back to exactly the same
form. So we can we can put a cross over
this term. This term is not invariant.
This term is invariant.
Lagrangian we wrote down is just not
invariant under
uh this transformation. What does it
mean? It means that
if we
uh
It means among other things that if we
did this operation on the field where we
rotated it from point to point, we would
change the energy of the field. We
change the Lagrangian. We change the
energy of the field. We change the
momentum in the field. It just isn't the
same configuration that we started with
and it's not a configuration that has
the same properties. Now is has
different equations of motion, different
Lagrangian.
All right, so our first conclusion then
is that the Lagrangian
the complex scalar Lagrangian
has an invariance under rigid phase
rotations, but it is not invariant under
gauge transformations. Gauge
transformations mean these non-rigid
rotations where you vary differently at
different points.
Let me stop there and take any questions
that come up.
Because this is the essence and the
heart of
uh
of modern field theory basically, this
being the simplest example.
Yes. Can you help me with this phi
notation there?
Uh
d mu
is that the same as d by d x mu?
Yes.
Yep. I will write down again
a whole bunch of equivalences.
d phi by d x mu
is equal to phi mu is equal to d mu phi.
Do I have any other names for it?
I don't think so.
But yes, these are things all mean the
same thing.
Okay, but
subscripts and superscripts
Subscripts and superscripts are
different.
Now how are they different?
They're not different if we let's see,
it's the time component which changes
when we I I think um Yeah. Right. Uh
that
Yeah, let me mean I may be off by a sign
here. This may be
possibly a minus sign there, but it uh
that's not the important issue here.
That second one doesn't have any
imaginary component, right? Cuz it was
it's supposed to there's supposed to be
complex conjugate to multiply. Sorry,
which uh phi Yeah, this has no imaginary
component to it.
Because it's something times its complex
conjugate.
But it still does remember this this uh
thing. Yeah, it looks like you
can sort of be combined with mu squared
or something. No, mu squared is a
different quantity. Oh. It's not a mu.
You of course everybody realizes this mu
has nothing to do with the mu in the
in uh these meters, right?
I probably should call it m squared. You
could get rid of the of the imaginary
function
Are you going to continue on this? Hm?
You going to continue to expand this out
or Oh, if you like, I can. Yeah, let's
do it.
All right, so this is d mu phi
d mu phi star.
Oh, I guess one of these should have
upper indices, shouldn't they?
Uh I'm not sure how to do that.
Uh
Okay, I know what to do.
Do you learn anything if you extend it
out? Hm? No.
But, let's do it anyway.
D mu phi
and then
D mu theta.
Oops, D mu theta.
Do you learn anything if you expand it
out?
I don't see anything Hm? When you expand
it out, the first the first product it
just has two terms because imaginary
parts go away.
No.
Let's uh We will learn something.
Uh D mu phi star times D mu phi
Now, that's just the good old Lagrangian
uh
that we might have expected if there was
a symmetry.
Then, of course, there is minus I
D theta by DX mu.
Uh let's see. We're taking the cross
terms now. Let's Let's write Let me
write the cross terms uh carefully.
The two cross terms. They don't cancel.
Are you asking whether they cancel?
Yeah. No, they don't.
They do have an imaginary part. No,
let's Let's Let's see what they have.
They have minus I
D theta by DX mu.
All right. First of all, they multiply D
theta by DX mu, both of them.
This times this and this times this, the
two cross terms, all right? Both of them
have I's in them.
And one of them has Let's see what it
has.
It has
phi
times D mu phi star.
And then it has
minus phi star
D mu phi.
And then finally, we have minus I times
plus I is plus
D mu theta
D mu theta.
It's just the square of the sums the
sums or the differences of the squares
of various derivatives of theta times
phi star phi.
Okay?
Now, this does not cancel.
Phi derivative of phi star is not the
same thing as phi star times a
derivative of phi.
These two are complex conjugates of each
other. When you subtract them, you get
something pure imaginary and that
cancels this I here. Now, do you
remember this quantity?
It was uh something that was invariant.
I don't know how to say conserved, I
guess.
It was the current.
The current, J mu.
It's time component was the charge
density.
It's space component
was the current density.
Okay? Together,
they satisfied the
uh the flow equation, the um
continuity equation, right.
All right.
Okay, so we at least see something
familiar. Uh
And then this term over there is just
whatever it is, it's contains a phi star
phi, which I suppose we could combine
with this one minus m squared phi star
phi.
Good.
All right. So, yeah, we did learn
something, I think, by uh We fully
discovered this uh this um term here.
Good. So, answer is
no cigar, this Lagrangian is not
invariant under such a transformation.
But
if if that was the end of the story, of
course,
uh
we would go home and say this gauge idea
of gauge invariance is not important and
you know, 75 years of physics down the
drain.
Uh
All right. So,
let's see if we can force it to be
invariant. But, to do so, we have to add
another collection of fields.
To do so, we have to add another
collection of fields into the brew. And
to give those fields also transformation
properties under the same
transformation, we're going to have to
invent more fields and more
transformation properties to go with
them
uh in order to make this a symmetry.
The new fields that we're going to
invent are our first experience with
vector fields. Of course, we have some
vector fields. Anytime we differentiate
a scalar field, it's a vector field.
But now, we're going to invent some new
fields which are
how do I say, primordially
uh they are vector fields from the
beginning fundamental fields, they're
not derivatives of any other fields. And
we're going to give them a name, we're
going to call them A.
A mu.
Now, A mu has four components. I'm going
to tell you right now what they
correspond to so that we won't be
working in the blind
uh so that I won't just be doing
mathematical formalism on the
blackboard. If you know anything about
electromagnetism, you know that the
electromagnetic field tensor the
Sorry, I won't even use that word. That
the electric and magnetic fields can be
written
in terms of vector potentials and um
and a scalar potential.
Uh I won't write them down now, but
there are four quantities, the three
components of the vector potential and
the fourth is basically called the
electrostatic potential.
And those four quantities form a four
vector. The electrostatic potential
being the uh the time component and the
vector potential being the space
components of a four vector.
That's what these things are.
The time component
being uh well, we'll
being the electrostatic potential and
the other three components being the
space. Do you remember, for example,
what the magnetic field is in terms of
A, in terms of the uh space components?
No, cross curl. Yeah, it's the curl of
A.
And the electric field, something else.
Something else that can be written in
terms of these. We'll come to them what
they are.
Okay.
So, we're going to invent four more
fields. Now, these fields
unlike theta here
theta wasn't wasn't a dynamical field.
It's not something which has an equation
of motion. It was just a transformation
that we decided to do. We picked it at
will.
And when we picked it, we found out that
this was not a symmetry unless theta was
constant.
But now, we're adding more fields.
Okay?
And I'm going to add
I'm going to add this field and I'm
going to assume that it also transforms
under the same transformation. Now, what
do I mean by that? I mean there's some
transformation which involves all of the
variables.
Just in the same way uh that uh that if
I rotate
the coordinates of one particle, I also
need to rotate the coordinates of
another particle and so forth and so on.
There may be many degrees of freedom,
all which transform under the same
transformation.
So, we're going to assume Not that we're
going to basically postulate
that A also has a transformation
property or must have a transformation
property
whenever we do such a transformation.
And the transformation property is going
to be this.
It's going to be A mu.
Let's call it the uh
Hold on a second. I have
screwed up my notes here.
We seem to have notes from several
different lectures all mixed up
together.
Yeah.
Yeah, before we talk about the
transformation property of A
let's um
talk about how A fits into the
Lagrangian.
A is another variable which has an
equation of motion.
It will also have waves. Those waves
describe electromagnetic waves and so
forth. And A also has a Lagrangian of
its own.
Plus, there are interactions between A
and phi, which means there are things in
the Lagrangian which involve both A and
phi.
So, let's go back to the phi prime
Lagrangian. Let's go back to the phi
prime Lagrangian.
Our variables now are all our phi prime
phi complex conjugate prime and I'll
also call the vector potential, the
four-dimensional vector potential, A mu.
I'll call it prime for a moment.
Uh these are the prime variables. The
unprimed variables will be obtained from
these by some transformation. And the
Lagrangian for the
uh
prime variables, I'm now going to
modify.
I'm going to modify it to
D mu
phi star
prime.
Let's put the star on the outside.
Star out here. D mu
phi prime.
And now I'm going to add something. I
a constant called E. That constant will
ultimately appear as the electric charge
of the charged particle.
But, it's just a constant in the
Lagrangian now, a numerical number
times A prime
mu
phi prime.
What I've done is I've replaced just
derivative of phi
by a new thing, which is the derivative
of phi plus i a times the vector
potential times phi.
This is a new thing. It's actually
called the covariant derivative of phi,
but for the moment it's just a new
object. And we're going to multiply that
by Notice that it's complex conjugated.
Okay? When you complex conjugate, you
got to complex conjugate everything, phi
and i.
A is real.
A is real by assumption.
And that gets multiplied by
d mu phi prime
plus i e a prime
mu
phi prime.
Plus or minus m squared phi star phi.
So, I've modified the original starting
Lagrangian
by replacing the derivative of phi by a
new thing, derivative of phi or
derivative of phi prime plus i e a times
phi prime. Sometimes people write this
by saying just replace derivative with
respect to mu
by derivative with respect to mu plus i
e a mu.
Just replace the derivative operation by
derivative plus multiplication by i e a
mu. Right? So, sometimes one says that
this is a new replacement for the
derivative, which we call the covariant
derivative. Just a name.
This covariant has nothing to do with
the covariant from uh yeah.
Is are the phis at the very end of that
is that a phi or phi prime? Oh, sorry.
Uh phi prime.
Good. It actually doesn't matter, but uh
right.
Okay, right. Good.
All right. Now, supposing we carry
through
the same set of operations
and in other words, the same set of
operations where we're going to replace
phi prime by e to the i theta x phi.
What are we going to get?
Well, exactly the same thing is going to
happen and this derivative here is going
to get replaced by d mu
phi.
Where is it?
Uh
plus
I'll do the complex conjugation at the
end.
Plus i
d mu theta
Oops, lower d mu.
times phi.
That's what happens to derivative of phi
prime.
It just becomes derivative phi
plus i d mu theta times phi.
Okay? But now, we have to add plus i e
a prime mu
times phi.
Is this obvious what I've done or do I
need to explain it? I think I may need
to explain it a little more.
All I'm doing is replacing for phi prime
e to the i theta phi.
When I differentiate theta prime, I'll
get the extra term i d mu theta times
phi just as I did there. Oh,
incidentally, this also gets multiplied
I guess by e to the minus i theta.
All pieces and this should be complex
conjugated.
We can complex We can complex conjugate
it by just
All right. Stop me now if you don't
understand what I did. I I don't
understand what I did because I lost an
i.
Yeah.
Just complete substitution.
Wherever I saw
phi prime, I stuck e to the i theta
times phi.
That complex conjugate and then add in
the new term, the new hypothetical term
that I've added into the Lagrangian for
fun, for the fun of it, just to see what
happens.
That's one factor. The other factor will
cancel the e to the i theta.
This will cancel as before.
And what will have then is just the
complex conjugate of what's here, d mu
phi
plus i
d mu theta
times phi
plus i e
a prime mu
phi.
And let's forget the m squared phi star
Right, minus m squared
phi star phi.
Notice what's happened.
All that's happened Is there such a
thing as a
super mu?
Yeah, where a super mu. Good. This is
not
a one mu, it's just a prime mu, super
mu.
Yeah, if this has lower indices, then
the right hand side has to have upper
indices.
And uh that's it.
Okay, now look what's happened. What's
happened is um
the Lagrangian sort of has changed form
on the one hand.
It changed form or it started with in
that it now has this new term, but
there's another sense in which it hasn't
changed form. If I combine d mu theta
with a mu
if I define the combine those together
with a prime
in other words, if I take d mu theta
plus a as a plus Yeah, plus a prime
and I call that a
I just call that a
unprimed then this has exactly the same
form as it started with, except both phi
and a we've dropped their primes.
Has exactly the same form.
And so, that tells me that if I want to
maintain the symmetry, I had better
postulate a transformation property of
a, namely that you simply add the
derivative of theta to it
to define the new field after
transformation.
So,
to have
we
add another field into the brew
a mu
prime
and that's equal to a mu
plus
i No, no i.
d mu theta.
This is the full transformation property
or the full transformation um structure
of the three fields phi, phi prime phi
prime, phi star prime, and a. Actually,
how many fields are there?
Two here. Two two here and four more
here.
Six fields here. Six independent
components.
Uh the last symbol there is that a phi
or a theta? Where? On the a Theta.
Theta. Theta.
Okay, is that a function of x and t?
Yeah, it's a function of x. Otherwise,
how could you differentiate it?
Yeah, but it's not a function of time.
It could be. Oh, yeah. No, no, no, no.
Derivative with respect to mu means
derivative with respect to everything.
So, we're not just comparing reference
frames at different points of space,
also in time.
Right? We're imagining that our
coordinate uh our coordinates in this
angular space
can be rotated in space and they can
also be rotated uh they can be rotated
from point to point in space and point
to point in time.
So, let's just go through it again.
We started with a new Lagrangian, a new
a new field theory that contains a new
set of fields a
that enter into the old Lagrangian in
this new way.
Then we carried out the change of
variables from phi prime to phi and we
discovered that basically what it does
is it keeps the same form for the
Lagrangian except that we have to modify
a prime and add to it the derivative of
theta.
This is the full structure of a gauge
transformation.
And if we make these substitutions, if
we make these substitutions into the
original Lagrangian
then the form of the Lagrangian does not
change.
Then the form of the Lagrangian does not
change
and we can write that this is equal to
I'm just going to I'm just going to
replace this
exactly the same thing except with all
the primes dropped.
All right.
This is equal to
same thing
without
primes.
That's the idea of a symmetry. If the
Lagrangian has exactly the same form
both before and after the
transformation, then you say there's a
symmetry.
So, this new field theory, whatever it
is
uh
is invariant under local gauge
transformations. Local means that the
that the that the
phase parameter here can depend on
position.
Gauge invariant. The Lagrangian is gauge
invariant or the action is gauge
invariant.
invariant
E to the one
I mean
A prime
Yeah.
Oh, that's not E that's not the
mathematical symbol 2.7128 whatever it
is.
This is the electric charge
of some particle. Now, what particle?
The quanta of the field described by
phi, but that's yet to be proved that in
any sense that this
that this has uh
Oh, you're right.
Uh one over E one over E
You're right.
one over E
Which one?
I thought it was plus. Let's see.
I thought it was plus.
Uh maybe
uh
No, I think you're probably right. I I
I think you may be right. Yeah.
Yeah, I think we had that A Yeah, you're
right. A was equal to A prime plus uh
the derivative, I think.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Good. I think I
think we have it right now.
Okay. So,
what we've discovered up till now was we
can force, if you like, we can force a
field theory to have this new kind of
invariance where you transform things
from place to place, not just rigidly.
In fact, the only real symmetries of
nature are gauge symmetries like this.
Uh
all others
are not really symmetries of nature.
Not Not yet. Not yet. Not yet. Not yet.
Um
All right. Now,
what I haven't indicated here
is whether there's other terms in the
Lagrangian governing A, for example.
The phi part of the Lagrangian We've
seen what the phi part of the Lagrangian
corresponds to. It's out of phi Oh,
incidentally, yeah. Um
Same thing without primes.
Notice how A
enters into the Lagrangian
uh
What will happen to this this form of
the Lagrangian when we uh
when we put
A prime in or A in?
This will get replaced by A.
So, in fact,
the Lagrangian, which I can write as
having uh as a plus I think it's plus
plus E times A prime
this whole thing just becomes E error
becomes A.
Now, I don't know how familiar it is uh
Did I leave out
E? I think I left out E. Yeah. E.
E A mu
I don't know whether this str- strikes a
bell or rings a bell to you or not. Um
Do you know what the Lagrangian for a
current
in an electromagnetic field looks like?
An electric current in an in a in an
electromagnetic field?
In particular, magnetic field.
No, that No, no. Not A dot B. Not A dot
B.
P goes to momentum goes to momentum less
E times the vector potential. This is
true, and that's one way of seeing it.
But, if we're talking about a you know,
uniformly flowing a current of some
sort, not an individual particle.
What the What is the coupling of a
current to the electromagnetic field?
Okay, I'll tell you right now.
What is it? A times that current. A
times that current. A dot J.
A dot J. We're going to We're going to
come We're going to come back to this.
We're going to come back to this.
A dot J
uh
And more generally, this would be the
case if there was only a space
component. This would be the coupling of
a magnetic field to a current.
Well, that's about what we see here. We
see J
and we see A. So, we see the pieces plus
a time component piece. We see the
pieces
that uh are traditionally the
interaction between electric and
sorry, electric charges or electric
currents
and
uh
and um
electric currents and the
electromagnetic field. Electromagnetic
field is best described in terms of the
vector potential. And the electric and
magnetic fields are things that we build
up out of the electric out of the vector
potential. Okay. Now, let's um let's
talk about
the electromagnetic field when there are
no charge charges and currents. In other
words, let's forget about phi. Let's
forget about phi
and ask what kind of theory describes A
by itself.
What we're talking about now is
electromagnetic waves propagating in the
absence of charges. Supposing we just
forget phi. Phi is a thing which
describes the charged currents.
It's the thing in quantum mechanics
which describes the charged particles.
The charged particles are quanta of this
field. But, let's forget charges. We
know that electromagnetic
electromagnetism has an interesting
non-trivial
behavior even far from where there are
any charges. Namely, electromagnetic
waves propagating through empty space.
So, there must be some dynamics
to the electromagnetic field which is
even there in the absence of charges.
So, it's not this. It's something just
involving the electromagnetic field
itself
when
this field phi is equal to zero.
Oh, this incidentally, this would become
A squared here. A mu A mu.
So,
what shall we say governs the
electromagnetic field by itself? Well, I
would like to maintain this gauge
symmetry. If I'm going to go to all of
this effort to invent A just to make
this
this this Lagrangian gauge invariant, I
certainly don't want to destroy that
gauge invariance by uh by
not having the electromagnetic field
Lagrangian by itself be gauge invariant
by not having it. So, we want the
electric the wanted the Lagrangian
that we make up, let's call it L,
that part of it which depends on the
vector potential in various ways. The
vector potential and its derivatives.
Right?
We want that Lagrangian also to be gauge
invariant.
So, that brings up the question then,
what kind of combinations can I make up
out of just the electromagnetic out of
just A by itself?
The four components of A.
What kind of combinations can I make up
uh in particular, out of the derivatives
of A. I'm mostly interested in the
derivatives of A. It's typically
derivatives of fields which enter into
Lagrangians. There may also be things
without derivatives, but Lagrangians
most important thing is dependence on
the velocities, the the derivatives.
So, what kind of thing can I make out of
the derivatives of A
that itself is gauge invariant that
might enter into Lagrangian?
Yeah. That's right. With A transforming
uh with A transforming in this way.
In other words, invariant under
A goes to A
minus one over E
times the derivative of
theta. For arbitrary theta. Any theta is
allowed. You pick it. We want the
Lagrangian to not change when we do this
operation. Let's put some indices in
here.
Okay.
All right. Uh let's
uh let's see if we can figure out. Let's
look at the various derivatives of A.
There are all of the There are four
components of A, and there are four
distinct derivatives that we can do.
That means there are 16 derivatives of A
that we can concoct.
Derivative with respect to X of A sub X,
derivative with respect to Y of A sub X,
and so forth. There are 16 of them since
there are four components of X and four
components of A. They can all be
summarized in the form D nu
A mu.
Mu can go from zero to three, that's
four components. Nu can go from zero to
three. And so this is just a convenient
way to represent basically a matrix of
16 independent derivatives of the four
components of A.
Let's see what happens to this
when we make a gauge transformation.
When we make a gauge transformation
A mu will go to A mu minus 1 over E D mu
theta.
So this will go to
D nu of
A mu
minus I 1 over Sorry, minus 1 over I
minus 1 over E
D mu theta.
In other words, it will pick up an extra
term. The change in D nu theta
will be the extra term is the extra term
will be
minus 1 over E
D nu
D mu
theta.
D nu D mu theta. What does this mean?
This means the second partial
derivative.
First you differentiate with respect to
X mu and then you differentiate with
respect to X nu. Everybody understand
what this symbol is? D nu D mu theta?
It's the second partial derivative of
theta
with respect to X nu and X mu.
Okay, that in itself
suggests
if you're you know, if you fiddle with
these things at all, it would
immediately suggest what the invariant
quantity you can make. Let's look at the
at the
related quantity. This could for example
be
if nu was one, let's take the case nu
equals one, mu equals two.
That would mean derivative with respect
to X of A sub Y for example.
One corresponds to X, Y corresponds to
two.
There's another quantity which also has
an index X and an index Y in it and it's
sort of the opposite. It's D Y A X.
Okay. We can represent the matrix of
those variables
as D mu
A nu.
All right, so if X's if if nu is one and
mu is two, then this could be D X of A Y
and this would be D Y of A X. But there
are each one has 16 components. What
happens to this quantity
when you make a transformation? Well, it
All I have to do is swap mu mu and nu. I
don't have to do much work. It goes to
D mu A nu. All I've done is interchange
mu and nu.
And then
minus
D nu
No, D mu D nu A.
D mu D nu theta.
All I've done is interchange mu and nu.
Okay, so D nu this goes to
minus D nu D mu
theta.
What happened to the E? You divide by E.
Yes, 1 over E.
Good.
Now it's pretty clear what to do to make
something which doesn't change under a
gauge transformation. Just Oh, well,
first of all
the theorem. The theorem is that the
order of differentiation
of a variable of a function is
immaterial.
The derivative with respect to mu times
the derivative with respect to nu is the
same as the derivative interchanged.
All right. For example, the derivative
with respect to X of the derivative with
respect to Y of theta is the same as the
derivative sub Y derivative sub X of
theta. Order of
Order of operations for derivatives
doesn't matter.
D X D Y is the same as D Y D X.
So
that means that D nu D mu theta is the
same as D mu D nu theta.
Supposing I subtract these two things
and define a new quantity
D nu A mu
minus D mu A nu. That's not zero.
We're not subtracting the same thing.
We're not subtracting a thing from
itself. We're subtracting for example D
X A Y from D Y A X. That's not zero.
But what happens to it under a gauge
transformation? Nothing happens to it
because the shift cancels out. The
change in the two of these is the same
and when you subtract them
the change cancels out. So under a gauge
transformation, this just goes to
itself.
D nu A mu minus D mu A nu. How many such
quantities are there?
16 to begin with. 16. There are 16
quantities which are all invariant. All
16 of them are invariant under gauge
transformations. Now, there actually
aren't 16
or at least there aren't 16 non-trivial
ones.
10 of them 10 of them?
Well, 10
First of all, four of them are zero.
All the ones in which nu and mu are the
same. We can make a matrix out of these.
We can make a matrix out of these, a 4
by 4 matrix.
Label the matrix entries 0 1 2 3
0 1 2 3 and then in each entry we could
put
the appropriate D nu A mu minus D mu A
nu. I think you get the idea. What
happens on the diagonals here?
They're zero. This is D 1 A This is D 0
A 0 minus D 0 A 0.
Here we would have D 1 A 1 minus D 1 A
1. So all the diagonal entries are zero.
It's anti-symmetric. Yes. It's
anti-symmetric which means when you
interchange mu and nu, it changes sign.
So first of all, it's zero along the
diagonal.
There are some entries off the diagonal.
For example, over here we would have I
think D 1 A
0 I think minus D 0 A 1.
What would we have down here?
The opposite with the opposite sign
because when we interchange mu and nu
the minus sign here causes it to flip.
So whatever we have above the diagonal
here, we have exactly the same thing
below the diagonal except with the sign
changed. So there's no use of keeping
track of the things above the diagonal
and below the set diagonal separately.
They're so closely related, they're just
opposites from each other that they're
not independent. And so how many
independent quantities are there?
There's all the ones above the diagonal.
That's it. 1 2 3 4 5
6.
Six independent
derivatives of this type that we can
form. Six independent components
of this anti-symmetric object.
What are those six independent
components? I mean
I will tell you now. I'm not going to I
don't want to hide it and jump out and
surprise you with it. The six
independent components are the three
independent components of the electric
field
and the three independent components of
the magnetic field.
Like we could put them up in here. The
three independent components of the
electric field
are up in here.
I'll specify I'll be more precise about
them later. And the three independent
components of the magnetic field are
here.
For the moment
we're just counting how many independent
quantities are there? Six. How many
independent components of the electric
and magnetic field are there? Six. It
sounds like they may be related. In
fact, they are the same thing. But the
precise connections between them we'll
come back to.
All right, this object here, D nu A mu
minus D mu A nu
which is made up out of first
derivatives of A
There's a symbol for it and a name for
it. It's called the electromagnetic
field tensor.
Okay.
It's called the electromagnetic field
tensor and it consists of the components
of electromagnetic field E and B
and the symbol for it
is F
nu mu.
So F is just a complex of six objects
that forms an anti-symmetric tensor
whose components are really in disguise
the electric and magnetic fields.
We'll come back to them.
But now we have something that we can
build a gauge invariant Lagrangian out
of.
In fact, this is the only thing which is
gauge invariant and made up out of the
first derivatives of A.
What kind of thing would we like to have
in a Lagrangian for A?
Well, Lagrangians are usually functions
of the variables in their first
derivatives.
In fact, that's always the case.
Lagrangians are functions of the
variables in their first derivatives.
Which variables are we talking about?
We're talking about the A's.
Anything which doesn't have derivatives
in it, A A squared,
uh anything like that is not going to be
gauge invariant. It just won't. A will
change under a gauge transformation and
any simple function of A that doesn't
contain derivatives will not be gauge
invariant.
The only thing that's easy to make up
that's gauge invariant that contains A
and its first derivatives
is F mu nu. That's it. That's the only
gauge invariant quantities that there
are
which contain no more than first
derivatives
and
uh that's it. So, what can you do to
make a Lagrangian
that had that's quadratic in
derivatives?
Supposing we want to stick to this
pattern of things which are quadratic in
the derivatives
and which is Lorenzen invariant.
Let's come back now. There's another
invariance that we wish to keep track of
and that's Lorenzen invariance.
To keep track of Lorenzen invariance by
now should be very easy.
All we have to do is contract indices,
upper and lower indices.
As long as all indices are contracted
correctly,
then Lorentz transformations will be a
symmetry of anything that we make.
It's pretty obvious there's only one
thing that we can make. It's F nu mu
F nu mu.
This is basically sums and differences
of squares of the components of F.
I'll tell you exactly what it is.
It's E squared, the electric field
squared minus the magnetic field
squared.
E squared minus B squared. Now, we're
going to come and we're going to study
the nature of this field tensor
and its relation to the electric and
magnetic fields in more detail,
but I'm sort of outlining and sketching
where we're going
that we were forced So, let's summarize.
If we wanted to have this peculiar gauge
invariance,
then we were forced to introduce a new
variable called A.
A itself
had a transformation property
and it entered into a new structure
called the covariant derivative. Where
is the covariant derivative?
D mu
plus I E A mu
is the covariant derivative.
Then we discovered that if in the
original Lagrangian we replaced all
derivatives by covariant derivatives,
that's the operation. Replace all
and at the same time allow the vector
potential to have its own transformation
property,
then the Lagrangian was invariant under
these gauge transformations.
So, that's a kind of pretty thing that
that there is a
Lagrangian that we can write down
that generalizes the original Lagrangian
which has this improved symmetry, this
more powerful symmetry or this bigger
symmetry where you can vary the phases
from point to point in space.
Well, then we said,
"Good. Now, let's talk about A by
itself.
We've motivated why A has a certain
gauge transformation property.
Now, let's ask can we make Lagrangians
for A by itself which have this gauge
transformation property that they're
invariant?
And so, we looked around for expressions
which would not transform when you make
a gauge transformation.
In fact, we looked around for things
that we could make up out of the
derivatives. These are the 16 possible
derivatives of A.
And the obvious answer
is the antisymmetric quantity D nu A mu
minus D mu A nu.
For that,
this extra piece which gets induced by
the gauge transformation
cancels.
So, we found a gauge invariant, F mu nu.
Anything that we make out of F mu nu
will be gauge invariant, but not
anything that we make will be Lorenzen
invariant.
Just F mu nu by itself is not Lorenzen
invariant. It has open indices hanging
around here.
No, it's that's what I mean when I say
it's not invariant. Yeah, it's not a
scalar.
It's not a scalar. It has open indices
here. It has components. So, it'll
transform in various ways.
But,
if we square it
and contract the indices in the right
way,
it will become something which is
Lorenzen invariant. And in fact, it is
just E squared minus B squared. Now,
it's not obvious that this is Lorenzen
invariant, but it is.
E squared minus B squared is a quantity
which is
the same in every Lorentz frame.
If we have an electric field someplace
and a magnetic field and we look at it
from a different
state of motion
or a different angle,
the electric and magnetic field
components will transform. In fact, if
we view an electric field from a moving
frame, we'll typically see a magnetic
field. If we view a magnetic field from
a moving frame, we'll see an electric
field.
But, whatever E squared minus B squared
is, it's the same in every reference
frame.
Uh
that's the content
of this expression. E squared minus B
squared is invariant because all the
indices are properly contracted. So, now
we have a candidate
for the action of the electromagnetic
field itself. We're not going to work
out the equations of motion tonight.
We'll do that another time,
but I'm showing you the logic that went
into uh to the idea of gauge symmetry.
Um
Well, let's let's continue.
That's really in a sense enough for one
night, isn't it?
Uh Are you going to go into what's
conserved because you have a symmetry or
Yes. Well,
um
Not tonight, though, but I may. I mean,
yeah, we we I like to do that. Yes. Can
you go back to the analogy of the
spinning rope and and describe Is it
possible to describe
A in
regards to that analogy? Well, I'll tell
you that the
No, I can't do that at this moment
because the analogy involves general
relativity.
Um
Let's put it this way.
In the rope analogy, the core the uh
these uh variables uh phi are actually
coordinates of positions of the rope.
So,
what we're talking about when we make
these kind of transformations is
coordinate transformations
which vary from place to place.
Coordinate transformations which vary
from place to place are the material of
the general theory of relativity.
So, until we would come to the general
theory of relativity, that jump rope
would not look gauge invariant,
but it is gauge invariant uh when
gravity is taken. But, this is beyond
right now beyond the level of the course
at the moment.
Uh if and when we get to study general
relativity, remind me to come back to
this and we can see how the jump rope
also has its own gauge invariance, but
not now. It's not uh
The vector potential would be certain
components of the gravitational field.
Certain components of the gravitational
field which are there in the general
theory of relativity would become the
analog of the vector potential.
So,
it's it's it's a correct question. It's
a good question, but it's it's beyond uh
beyond um
our level at the moment.
All right. I think I'm just going to go
on a little more
uh and tell you a totally different way
which is
which of course is secretly exactly the
same way
of thinking about the electromagnetic
field and its interaction with
particles. This is the electromagnetic
field and its interaction with charged
wave fields.
Phi is a charge carrying wave field.
That's the language one would use or a
charge carrying scalar field
that carries charge in the sense that
waves of this field
uh constitute electric charge densities
and electric
uh currents.
And here we see the basic interaction
A.J. which is the hallmark of the
interaction of charges with the vector
potential.
Uh
Of course, we might
Now, uh
when we study quantum mechanics,
the particle field duality or the
particle field complementarity or
whatever Bohr wanted to call it, tells
us that all fields are associated also
with particles. And in fact, the phi
field is is
with charged particles.
But,
we don't need to study quantum mechanics
to figure out how char to figure out to
describe how charged particles interact
with the electromagnetic field. We can
just go back
to the basic particle description of
charges
and ask in that language, the original
particle classical particles with
carrying charge, how do they interact
with the electromagnetic field?
And so, I want to completely change
gears and go back to classical particles
in the special theory of relativity.
Classical particles, the Lagrangian for
classical particles in the special
theory of relativity,
and then show you how the
electromagnetic field responds,
and in particular, we'll also see the
idea of gauge invariance.
Takes on a different form, has a
different flavor to it, but it's the
same invariance.
Okay. So, let's think of a world line of
a particle. Here's the world line of a
particle.
The world line
has to be chosen subject to the rules of
of the principle of least action.
And so, our first question is what is
the action of a
moving particle moving in the special
theory of relativity? For the moment,
let's forget fields. No fields in the
problem, just a free particle.
Well, there's really only one invariant
that we can make for a trajectory that
in any way looks anything like an
action.
The natural quantity to identify with a
trajectory is the length of the
trajectory.
Mhm.
The length of the trajectory
is the rela the the relativistic length
of the trajectory.
The relativistic length of the
trajectory is the natural quantity to
identify with the action.
Uh in any case, it's a candidate. And
the reason it's a good candidate is
because it's invariant.
It's invariant, the the proper time
I should say the length of the
trajectory, I mean the proper time along
the trajectory.
The proper time along the trajectory is
basically the action of a trajectory of
a particle.
Well, not quite. You'll have to multiply
the proper time along the trajectory by
the mass.
And for reasons which are pretty much
conventional,
there's a minus sign.
Ah,
I hate these things.
Have we run out of them?
Let's see.
Minus.
Minus m, the mass of the particle,
times the proper time between the
initial point and the final point along
the trajectory. But what's the proper
time? Well, let's start with the proper
time along a little piece of trajectory.
That's d tau squared
is equal to d t squared
minus the x squared plus the y squared
plus the z squared. I'm just going to
write the x squared here.
In fact, let's
That stands for the x squared plus the y
squared plus the z squared. I let me
write it out once in full. Minus the y
squared minus the z squared
equals
d t squared
minus the x squared.
And the x I I suppose I could put a
little arrow over this.
The x squared.
All right.
That's d t squared. That's the proper
time squared of a small little interval.
There are some speeds of light which
would go in here. If we had speed of
light, where would they go?
Uh
I'm going to leave them out.
They don't add anything to the
discussion at this point.
Okay. So, this is d tau squared, and d
tau, the actual proper time along the
trajectory, is just the square root of
this.
So, let's get rid of the c squareds cuz
we don't
cuz we're grown-ups and we don't need to
take the speed of light to not be equal
to one.
And d tau is equal to the square root of
this.
The total path The total path length, or
the total proper time along the path
length, is an integral.
The integral from the beginning to the
end along the trajectory
of the square root of d t squared, and
I'm just going to write minus the x
squared, but please keep in mind that
that the x squared stands for the x
squared plus the y squared plus the z
squared.
Okay.
That's the action. Now, what on earth
does this mean? The square root of the
square of a differential.
Uh all right. First of all, what it
means is chop up the trajectory into
little pieces,
calculate the square root of d t squared
minus the x squared along the trajectory
for each for each little piece and add
them up. Basically, that's all. Add them
up.
That's what the symbol means,
but we can make it look like a more
conventional integral
by dividing
inside the square root
and then multiplying out here.
I've multiplied basically multiplied and
divided by d t.
But if I put a d t under the square
root, it becomes d t squared.
All right. So, what's in the square root
here? What's in the square root is the
integral
Sorry, what's in the square root is one
d t squared minus d over d t squared one
minus Now, what's the x by d t?
It's speed of light. d t squared. It's
the velocity. This is the square of the
velocity. The square of the three
components of the velocity summed. The x
squared plus the y squared plus v c v c
v z squared.
So, this is just let me call it x dot
squared.
Dot means derivative with respect to
ordinary time, not proper time. x dot
squared, and of course, it stands for x
dot squared plus the y dot squared plus
the z dot squared. And I could also call
it just v squared if I wanted, but I'm
going to leave it there as x dot
squared.
times d t. Can we call it one over
cosine hyperbolic? No, I don't want to
call it anything. I just want to express
it in terms of the velocity itself.
Minus m.
Well, now I have a thing which looks
like a Lagrangian.
I should put the minus m on the inside.
Let me put it on the inside in here.
I'll put the minus sign also. Minus m
square root of one minus x dot squared.
Lagrangians are all are actions are
always integrals over Lagrangians.
Integrals with respect to time of
Lagrangians. Now, we're not talking
about field theory. We're just talking
about the motion of a particle.
So, there's no integration over space.
The degree of freedom now is just x.
x, y, and z of t.
The position of the particle as a
function of time
is
the degrees of freedom. Here is the
Lagrangian which depends on velocities.
It happens it doesn't depend
independently on x. It only depends on x
dot. Well, this is the kind of
Lagrangians we've seen in the past. It's
a little bit unusual. Instead of having
an x dot squared as a square root of one
minus x dot squared, but it falls within
the class of Lagrangians which depend on
the velocities and the coordinates.
So, it is a special case of
a conventional Lagrangian.
Let's use that first of all to calculate
the momentum.
What's the formula in terms of a
Lagrangian for the momentum conjugate to
x? Do you remember?
Derivative of the Lagrangian. This whole
thing is Lagrangian here.
Derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to x
x dot.
All right. So, now we get to try out our
skills
at differentiating. This is x dot Let me
put y dot squared plus z dot squared.
Okay.
Anybody good at differentiating?
Equals.
There's a minus m.
And then we have to differentiate a
square root.
That gives us a square root in the
denominator with a two.
Square root of one minus Now, let me
call it v squared.
x dot squared plus y dot squared plus z
dot squared. And then we have to
differentiate the argument of the square
root with respect to x dot.
All right. So, that gives us a minus
another minus sign, a two,
and an x dot.
The twos cancel.
And we get m
times x dot, or better yet, m times the
x component of the velocity
over the square root of one minus v
squared.
I think we saw that before. We have
studied this, have we not? Right.
This is v squared over c squared if we
were to put the c's back in.
Well,
that's nice.
Uh we've We see that the
canonical momentum is just the momentum.
The relativistic momentum, mass times
velocity, with the Einstein correction
square root of 1 minus V squared over C
squared in the denominator.
What about the energy?
What about the energy of the particle?
Uh the energy is the Hamiltonian.
So if you have to go back to your
classical mechanics and but I'll tell
you what the answer I'm going to just
tell you the answer.
Uh
It's a little bit of of algebra that
goes into it but I'll tell you what you
what you have to do.
The Hamiltonian of a system is the sum
over the degrees of freedom
of
the velocities
times
the momenta
minus the Lagrangian. Do you remember
that formula?
All right.
So we have this
There's only one coordinate now or three
coordinates to be more precise. Three
coordinates X Y and Z.
So for example one of the terms will be
um
X dot That's Q dot
times P sub X times M V sub X over the
square root of 1 minus V squared over C
squared.
And then we have to subtract off the
Lagrangian
which is
plus M square root of 1 minus V squared.
Okay.
A little bit of algebra not much will
convince you
Hm?
But
Another factor of
So Oh.
Uh yeah there's let's let's get rid of
the factors let's get rid of the C's
you're right. Let's just get rid of
them.
Yeah.
Uh because I've been
I've been loose in the coefficients of C
here and other places let's just leave C
equal to 1.
Uh
Oh let's This isn't so hard.
Uh this is V X dot times VX is VX
squared right?
M
Oh. Of course there's also contributions
from Y and Z.
So this VX squared will become M VX
squared plus VY squared plus VC squared.
We should have added up the three the
three terms.
This just becomes M V squared.
All three components.
Plus M So let's see so what is this?
Let's put them over a common
denominator.
Let's put them both over the same common
denominator square root of 1 minus V
squared. Let's get rid of the square
root here.
The V squared is cancel and we just get
M over the square root of 1 minus V
squared.
Have we seen that before?
Yeah.
That's the energy. If we wanted to give
it proper units of energy when the C's
are in there it would be MC squared over
V squared over C squared.
And that would be the energy of the
particle.
All right that's the canonical
formulation of a particle in special
relativity not under the influence of
any force field.
All right. The question is what happens
when we include an electromagnetic
field?
Now I'm getting tired so the question is
yeah let's see if I let's
It's rather easy but uh
Okay let's let's do it.
I don't want to stop here because we're
going to be gone for a week
and I guess I'd like to finish the the
line of argument and then have everybody
study it in some detail.
Suppose there's an electromagnetic
field. An electromagnetic field is
described by a vector potential A mu.
So let's suppose there's a vector
potential or a four-dimensional vector
potential A mu.
How can I combine it with the particle
to make an action
that involves the particle moving in the
electromagnetic field? I'm not talking
about the action of the electromagnetic
field now just the particle
the influence of the electromagnetic
field on it.
So what can I do with an A mu and a
particle trajectory to make something
that involves A mu and the particle
trajectory which is Lorenzen variant?
Well there's not too many things Well
first of all you could think of an
infinite variety of things but most of
them would be exceedingly complicated.
There's one simple thing
that you can write down.
Uh anybody know what it is? A dot V.
Well this is a four vector.
That's a four vector.
So we don't want to use a conventional
velocity
DX DT.
A dot P.
Hm? A dot P.
P is not a thing that you usually put in
Lagrangians.
We usually put in
All right but
let's uh
There's a simple thing.
Instead of A dot
V
instead of A dot
V which is on the right track
let's try
A
times not V mu but DX mu by D tau.
But wait a minute.
That's That's okay this is an
interesting quantity A mu times DX mu by
D tau. This is a four vector DX mu by D
tau but this is not conventional
velocity.
And um
It looks a little bit awkward. But let's
take the action. Let's try to use this
in an action. What's the natural thing
to do with this? The natural thing to do
with it is to integrate it along the
trajectory. But do you integrate it DT?
And if not why not?
The answer is no you wouldn't want to
integrate it DT because this would not
be Lorenzen variant.
DT
is not Lorenzen variant. What is
Lorenzen variant is D tau.
Another way of saying the whole same
thing is we could include in the action
just the integral of A mu DX mu.
What does this mean? This means we go
along the trajectory we chop up the
trajectory
and for each little interval we take its
DX mu
and we multiply it by A mu.
A mu at that point.
A mu right at that point and we add them
up.
That's a quantity which is
relativistically invariant.
Why? Because it's the summation of a
bunch of scalars.
A mu DX mu a four vector with a lower
index times a four vector with an upper
index that's invariant that's a scalar.
And so we add them all up we get a
scalar.
This is a good quantity to
to begin with. Now I'm going to throw in
one more factor here I'm going to throw
in the electric charge that's just a
numerical multiple the electric charge
of the particle.
That ought to go in there. Why should it
go in there? Well if the electric charge
was zero then we should have no
interaction with the electromagnetic
field. So presumably the strength of
interaction between the electric and
magnetic fields on the one hand and the
particle is through its electric charge
so that's a reasonable thing to put in
there.
But this doesn't look like a
conventional Lagrangian.
Where is the velocity? Where is the
uh
uh where is the DT? Where is the
Lagrangian DT?
Well that's that's easy to fix. Just
divide by DT
and multiply by DT.
What does this mean?
It's integral E. Now let's take the time
component. The time component would be A
naught naught for time
times Now what's X naught? X naught is
T.
So that's just DT by DT. That's 1.
And then plus
electric charge
let's take the X component A sub X
times DX DT. What is DX DT? That's V sub
X right? That's the X component of the
velocity.
If we combine all of the terms we'll
just get A dot V.
DT.
So somebody earlier said that the
Lagrangian for somebody earlier said
that the interaction between the
the vector potential
and the charged particle was through A
dot V. Well yes that's right he see it
but there's another term integral A
naught.
This is the interaction this is the
Lagrangian
or or here this is the action
for a particle
in an electromagnetic field. It's very
simple it's just a line integral of A
dot DX. Do you have an E squared there?
E squared?
Yeah you have an E outside the
parentheses. Oh sorry.
Uh no no E squared.
You don't want that second
That's right.
Yeah. E times A dot V.
All right I don't want to pursue this
too much now other than to make one
observation about it. Just one
observation about it and that's that
it's that it's gauge invariant. That it
has a certain gauge invariance. That is
an action principle
thought of as an action principle, it
has a gauge invariance.
Uh so
Yeah, even before I do that, let me uh
relate uh let me relate some of this
stuff to what's over here.
Supposing I have a particle moving along
a trajectory like that.
And it's a charged particle.
There's an electric current that flows.
Uh both time component, there's an
electric charge density and there's a
flow of charge. The flow of charge is
just because the charge is moving. Now,
where is the uh where is the
electromagnet where is the
uh current localized?
It's localized wherever the particle is.
It's right sitting on top of the
particle. So, wherever the particle is,
there's a flow of current if the
particle is moving and there's a charge
density. The charge density is just
describing the charge density of that uh
single uh particle.
So, there's a flow So, there's a current
along the trajectory of the particle.
The space component of the current, the
flux of the charge, that's proportional
to the velocity of the charge. The If
the If the particle is not moving,
there's no flow of charge. There may be
a charge density, but there's no flow of
charge.
If a particle is moving, there's a flow
of charge. So, along this trajectory,
there is a J.
The time component is just the fact that
there's a charge there, a uh a um
a charge density at the point where the
particle is. And the space components of
J, what are they proportional to?
They're proportional to the electric
charge of the particle times its
velocity.
It's right at the point where the
particle is is a current which is
proportional to the velocity
in the direction of the velocity and of
course it also involves the electric
charge.
Well, let's see. Where did we have it?
We had the Lagrangian.
Here it is.
A dot V.
What is A dot V?
A dot V
uh um
It's clearly similar to
or E A dot V.
E times V is the current.
It's Where did I do it? I lost it.
Yeah, here it is. J is E times V.
E times V is the current. This is the
current dotted with the vector potential
dotted into the vector potential.
Well, that's pretty much what you have
over here. Current times vector
potential.
So, we see there's a similarity.
The similarity being that in both cases
the vector potential
is coupled directly to the uh to the
charge flow, to the flux of charge or to
the density of charge.
Uh and I just wanted to point out that
similarity at this point. That in both
cases it's charge current or current of
charge times vector potential which goes
into the Lagrangian. The last thing I
want to do is just talk about the gauge
invariance of this Lagrangian.
Is it gauge invariant?
Not quite, but almost and it's good
enough.
Let's look at the action
between two points.
What will it mean to say that the action
is gauge invariant? Well, supposing the
action changes
when I do a gauge transformation, but it
changes in a way that has no effect
whatever on the motion of a particle.
In other words, it changes in a way that
uh that has no implication whatever for
how the charge uh how the particle
moves. That's good enough to say that
there's a uh that there's a symmetry.
So, let's see what happens. Supposing I
make a gauge transformation on A mu.
What does that do? What does it add to A
mu?
A mu
goes to A mu
plus 1 over E
D mu theta where theta is just this
arbitrary
function
theta of X. Any function whatever, I can
make such a gauge transformation. What
happens to the action?
The action gets an extra piece to it.
We have to add to it
E
times the integral
of the change in A. That's 1 over E. It
cancels the E.
D mu theta.
That's the shift in A.
times the X mu dt d tau.
Well, just the X mu. Just the X mu.
Anybody know what this integral is?
From the starting point to the end point
along the trajectory.
The derivative of theta times dx mu. The
mu's derivative of theta times dx mu.
The difference? Yeah.
And It's just the difference of theta
between the end points of the integrand
or between the end points of the
integral.
This is the change Let's Let's break it
up into little pieces.
This is the change in theta when you
change X by a little bit times the
change in X.
Each little interval along here,
this integrand is just a change in theta
from going and going from one point to
the next. When you add them all up, it
just gives you the total change in theta
in going from the initial point theta
initial to theta final. Sorry, theta
initial.
Theta final.
This whole integral is just theta final
minus theta initial.
Well, why doesn't such a term in the
action
have any implication
for the trajectory?
Because it doesn't depend on the
trajectory. It just depends on the value
of the theta at the two end points
and it doesn't depend on the trajectory.
No matter what trajectory you select,
this integral here is always the same.
It's just the difference of theta at the
beginning and end of the trajectory.
So, if this contributes something which
doesn't depend on the trajectory, it
will not have any influence whatever
on what trajectory the particle takes.
And in that sense, this is not an
interesting contribution to the action.
Has no implication for the motion of the
particle. The important part of the
action doesn't change. The part which
really influences the particle does not
change when you make a gauge
transformation. So, we see from this
particle perspective that gauge
transformations are also important
invariances of the action of a charged
particle with the electromagnetic field.
So, this time
we're not talking about a field carrying
the charge, we're just talking about a
point charge moving through space.
Uh
So, we see from two different
perspectives
that gauge symmetry is a fundamental
symmetry of the interaction of charges
with the electromagnetic field. Okay.
Uh I will be gone next week. I have to
uh give a lecture someplace. A couple of
places.
And I'll be back the week after. Uh
how many lessons have we had so far?
Seven.
Eight? Seems to me it must be eight.
Yeah.
So, we have two more.
And I think we I think we're getting
somewheres.
We've, you know, but I want to What I do
want to go through now is the
electromagnetic field. The equations of
motion for the electromagnetic field.
Why F mu nu is collect connected to E
and B.
And
to see that the electromagnetic field
actually has the effects on a charged
particle that you would expect.
Namely, that uh that it exerts forces of
the electrical and magnetic kind.
Then, we could maybe spend a little bit
of time with this and see that uh the
flow of charge in this picture here also
behaves as you would expect for charges
flowing uh through space if the charges
were described by this field.
Okay, I think we're finished for
tonight.
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.